There's a little magic in all of us...almost all of us.
Encanto is a animation, comedy, family film directed by Byron Howard.
The tale of an extraordinary family, the Madrigals, who live hidden in the mountains of Colombia, in
a magical house, in a vibrant town, in a wondrous, charmed place called an Encanto.
The magic of the Encanto has blessed every child in the
family—every child except one, Mirabel.
But when she discovers that the magic surrounding the Encanto is in danger, Mirabel decides that
she, the only ordinary Madrigal, might just be her exceptional family's last hope.
Mirabel Madrigal (voice), played by Stephanie Beatriz.
Abuela Alma Madrigal (voice), played by María Cecilia Botero.
Bruno Madrigal (voice), played by John Leguizamo.
Isabela Madrigal (voice), played by Diane Guerrero.
Luisa Madrigal (voice), played by Jess Darrow.
Pepa Madrigal (voice), played by Carolina Gaitán.
Encanto is a 2021 American animated musical fantasy comedy
film produced by Walt Disney Animation Studios.
It was directed by Jared Bush, and Byron Howard and written by Charise Castro Smith and Bush, with
original songs written by Lin-Manuel Miranda and a score composed by Germaine Franco.
The film stars the voices of Stephanie Beatriz, María Cecilia Botero, John Leguizamo, Mauro Castillo,
Jessica Darrow, Angie Cepeda, Carolina Gaitán, Diane Guerrero, and Wilmer Valderrama.
Encanto follows a multigenerational Colombian family, the Madrigals, led by a matriarch whose children and grandchildren—except for Mirabel
Madrigal—receive magical gifts from a miracle, which they use to help the people in their rural community, called the Encanto.
When Mirabel learns that the family is losing their magic, she sets
out to find out why and save the family and house.
Encanto premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Hollywood, Los Angeles, on November 3, 2021, and
was released in the United States on November 24 over a 30-day theatrical run.
It was also released in RealD 3D, Dolby Cinema, 2D and D-BOX formats.
Despite underperformance at the box office, grossing $261.3 million worldwide against a $120–150
million budget, it was a ratings success after its release on Disney+ on December 24, 2021.
The film received acclaim for its characterization, music, animation, voice acting, emotional depth, and cultural
fidelity; reviews named magic realism and transgenerational trauma as the film's core concepts.
Publications have described Encanto as a cultural phenomenon, and executives had
begun referring to it as a "franchise" within a year of release.
The film was nominated for three awards at the 94th Academy Awards, winning Best Animated Feature, and received numerous other
accolades, including the Golden Globe Award for Best Animated Feature and the BAFTA Award for Best Animated Film.
The film's associated merchandise has seen significant success, and its soundtrack became a breakout sensation, reaching number one on the US Billboard 200 and UK Compilation Albums charts; "We Don't
Talk About Bruno" and "Surface Pressure" were its two most successful songs, with the former topping both the US Billboard Hot 100 and UK Singles Chart for multiple consecutive weeks.
A theme park attraction based on the film is set to
open at Disney's Animal Kingdom in 2027.
The film explores themes of strong woman, magic,
sadness, immigration, supernatural.
The tone is lighthearted.